"Reversing Early-Stage Prostate Cancer Progression
with a Plant-Based Diet and Lifestyle Program"
Higher consumption of
a healthy plant-based diet
was significantly associated
with a lower chance
of having an elevated PSA,
which can be a sign
of prostate cancer.
We're talking about
potentially cutting the odds
of having an elevated PSA
in half with diet.
The researchers concluded:
"This study provides
strong evidence
supporting the potential use
of plant-based foods
in the prevention
and treatment
of prostate cancer."
"Not so fast", replied
an editor of the journal,
"This paper certainly
doesn't present final,
convincing proof
that reduced PSA levels
due to a plant-based diet
in fact translate
into what we actually care
about: less prostate cancer."
Harvard cohort researchers
took up the mantle
to answer that question.
And indeed,
greater consumption
of a healthful
plant-based diet does appear
to reduce the risk
of getting prostate cancer
and dying from prostate cancer
by nearly half
for men under age 65.
And those adhering more to a healthy
plant-based diet who do get cancer
had 90 percent lower odds
of ending up with high-grade,
more severe prostate cancer
and appeared to be better able
to handle cancer treatment
and ended up with
better sexual function,
less incontinence,
and more vitality.
This is consistent with the role
of diet and nutrition
in the prevention and treatment
of cancer more generally,
where the evidence points
to a diet
with minimal animal products.
What if you already
have cancer though?
Study findings suggest that
adhering to plant-based diets
may be beneficial
for overall cancer survival
and may potentially improve
the prognosis for common cancers
such as breast, colorectal,
and prostate cancers.
It starts with
case reports like this.
A 73-year-old man
with prostate cancer
was placed
on a plant-based diet,
and within 10 days,
his tumor markers were down
about 75 percent.
But case reports
are like glorified anecdotes.
You can't know
if a healthier diet
and lifestyle actually help
until you run a randomized,
controlled trial
and put it to the test.
Dr. Dean Ornish,
famous for showing
the progression of heart disease
could be reversed,
opening up arteries
without drugs,
without surgery,
just a plant-based diet
and lifestyle program,
eliminating angina chest pain
in about three-quarters
of patients
within a matter of months.
He decided to move
from killer #1— heart disease—
to killer #2—cancer.
93 men with early-stage
watch-and-wait prostate cancer
were randomized
to either standard care
or a plant-based diet along
with walking and relaxation.
The cancer tended to get worse
in the control group
but comparatively better
in the plant-based group.
When blood from the patients
on the standard diet
was dripped onto prostate cancer
cells growing in a petri dish,
cancer cell growth rates
were cut by 9 percent.
Their bodies were doing the best
they could to beat back the cancer.
The blood of patients on the
plant-based program, though,
knocked down the cancer
growth by 70 percent.
Eating and living
more healthfully
made their blood stream almost eight
times less hospitable to cancer.
Now, this was after a year.
Subsequent studies
have shown that you can see
a significant
cancer-fighting effect
after less than two weeks
on a similar Pritikin-style
plant-based diet with exercise.
Ornish took biopsies from
the prostate cancer patients
before and after three months
and saw a significant change
in the expression
of more than 500 genes.
You can see the subtle shift
in gene regulation
from more red to more green.
The green denotes genes
that are being downregulated
under the lifestyle changes,
before and after.
Of course,
what we really care about
are disease outcomes.
By the two-year follow-up,
significantly more men
in the control group
had enough cancer progression
that they had to go
into treatment, for example,
five had to get
radical prostatectomies,
which can lead
to urinary incontinence
and impotence in 60 percent,
whereas none of the men
in the lifestyle group
were forced to go into surgery.
What about those
with more serious disease?
Researchers followed 10 patients
with recurrent prostate cancer,
meaning those whose
invasive cancer had to be cut
or burned out with radiation,
yet their PSA levels
started to rise again,
signaling the cancer was back.
There was no control group
per se in this study.
Each patient was
kind of their own control
before and after,
being asked to center
their diets around
more whole plant foods.
There was a significant decrease
in the rate of PSA rise,
suggesting a slowing
of cancer growth.
4 out of 10 patients
actually saw their PSA levels
go down,
suggesting the possibility
of at least some degree
of disease remission.
9 out of 10 had a reduction
in their rates of PSA rise
as well as an improvement
of their PSA doubling times,
which is a proxy for how fast
the tumor doubles in size.
The increase
in average doubling time
went from about 12 months
before the dietary change
to 112 months,
which is the largest that has
ever been reported in any kind
of dietary intervention trial
for recurrent prostate cancer.
What about
really advanced cancer,
stage four with spread
to distant organs?
Out of nine patients
willing to go on
a plant-based
macrobiotic diet,
three men experienced
long-term regression
of multiple
bone lesions,
compared to no regression
or healing
in nine matched
control subjects
who continued eating
the standard American diet.
Those on the healthier diet
went on to live
an average of 19 years more,
compared to those with
the same severity of cancer
not even living
for 4 years more, on average,
on their standard diet.
Now this was not
a randomized study,
so maybe it says something
about those
willing to eat healthfully
rather than
healthful eating itself.
But what's the downside?
As Dr. Ornish likes to say,
"The only side effects
are good ones."
A large number of patients
with metastatic prostate cancer,
for example,
die not from their cancer,
but rather
from non-cancer causes,
and the number one cause
is heart disease,
so, a heart-healthy diet
could only help.